<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Life on Joshua Rasband&#39;s website</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/life/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Life on Joshua Rasband&#39;s website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <managingEditor>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</webMaster>
    <copyright>Joshua Rasband (CC BY 4.0)</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Deliberate practice of self-mastery</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-17-deliberate-practice-of-self-mastery/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-17-deliberate-practice-of-self-mastery/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The single most important factor for success is having self-mastery.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Self-mastery is difficult to teach, but it can be cultivated. The key is to&#xA;developing self-mastery is proper stewardship of the reward circuits of your&#xA;brain. You need to make sure that your brain sends reward signal in ways that&#xA;will direct you to achieve your goals.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The main way that I have accomplished this is through deliberate practice. Every&#xA;time I want some kind of reward or break, I push myself to work just a little&#xA;longer before I reward myself. Then, when I accomplish my goal, the sense of&#xA;reward is associated with self-mastery, rather than giving in, thereby&#xA;reinforcing a sense of pleasure at delayed gratification.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The single most important factor for success is having self-mastery.</p>
<p>Self-mastery is difficult to teach, but it can be cultivated. The key is to
developing self-mastery is proper stewardship of the reward circuits of your
brain. You need to make sure that your brain sends reward signal in ways that
will direct you to achieve your goals.</p>
<p>The main way that I have accomplished this is through deliberate practice. Every
time I want some kind of reward or break, I push myself to work just a little
longer before I reward myself. Then, when I accomplish my goal, the sense of
reward is associated with self-mastery, rather than giving in, thereby
reinforcing a sense of pleasure at delayed gratification.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m now at a point where a lot of the pleasure in my day comes from the
knowledge that I have successfully achieved my goals. On nights when I force
myself to do the dishes and finish my homework before I let myself have dessert,
it&rsquo;s the sense of accomplishment that is the bigger reward.</p>
<p>This is a difficult pattern of thought to cultivate. It&rsquo;s taken me almost a
decade to get here. The rewards are enormous, however. The ability to say no to
basically any distraction or temptation in favor of accomplishing my goals has
been of critical importance as I try to balance my many responsibilities and
goals.</p>
<p>As a final note, self-mastery does not have to mean that every waking moment is
spent working or studying. It just means that your decisions are more fully
yours. I have found that self-mastery has actually increased my enjoyment of
leisure activities, because I can engage in them with the knowledge that I have
picked leisure because it is what I want to do, not because it is easy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Values vs. tastes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-15-values-vs-tastes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-15-values-vs-tastes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After I got married, I learned an important lesson: there is a big difference&#xA;between differences in taste and differences in values. Differences in taste are&#xA;easy to live with and usually easy to compromise on. Differences in values are&#xA;basically impossible to come to a satisfactory compromise on. The way you like&#xA;your scrambled eggs is a taste. Whether you think it&amp;rsquo;s morally justified to be&#xA;eating eggs at all is a value.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>After I got married, I learned an important lesson: there is a big difference
between differences in taste and differences in values. Differences in taste are
easy to live with and usually easy to compromise on. Differences in values are
basically impossible to come to a satisfactory compromise on. The way you like
your scrambled eggs is a taste. Whether you think it&rsquo;s morally justified to be
eating eggs at all is a value.</p>
<p>What&rsquo;s the difference between a taste and a value? I think a taste is basically
a personal preference which you recognize is not intrinsically superior to other
preferences. In contrast, a value is something that you believe in because you
view it as being better or more true than other, competing values. Values are
not viewed as a matter of preference, which makes them more difficult to
compromise on.</p>
<p>Although it&rsquo;s much more difficult to find compromise when there&rsquo;s a difference
of values, a values-centered discussion can be very meaningful and productive.
It&rsquo;s very much possible to have one set of values, yet respect deeply another
person&rsquo;s commitment to a different set of values. Values are also typically not
a choice between right and wrong, but a choice between many good options, one of
which is deemed most important. When you understand someone at the level of
their values, you gain far more insight into their reasoning than if you were to
understand them at a more superficial level.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Find joys that satiate you</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-14-find-joys-that-satiate-you/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-14-find-joys-that-satiate-you/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some activities are &amp;lsquo;satiating&amp;rsquo;&amp;mdash;when you&amp;rsquo;re done, you don&amp;rsquo;t have an increased&#xA;desire to do or consume more. Think about a meal that leaves your hunger totally&#xA;satisfied. That kind of a pleasure is the kind of pleasure that we ought to be&#xA;spending most of our time on, in contrast to things that, like potato chips, never&#xA;satisfy the desire they were supposed to address in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many modern forms of entertainment, such as social media and streaming&#xA;television, don&amp;rsquo;t satiate. As a result, people spend much more time consuming&#xA;than they intend to. To continue the analogy, they wanted to satisfy their&#xA;hunger, but instead of eating a meal, they opened up a bag of potato chips.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some activities are &lsquo;satiating&rsquo;&mdash;when you&rsquo;re done, you don&rsquo;t have an increased
desire to do or consume more. Think about a meal that leaves your hunger totally
satisfied. That kind of a pleasure is the kind of pleasure that we ought to be
spending most of our time on, in contrast to things that, like potato chips, never
satisfy the desire they were supposed to address in the first place.</p>
<p>Many modern forms of entertainment, such as social media and streaming
television, don&rsquo;t satiate. As a result, people spend much more time consuming
than they intend to. To continue the analogy, they wanted to satisfy their
hunger, but instead of eating a meal, they opened up a bag of potato chips.</p>
<p>Look at your day and think about the things that you spend time doing. Why do
you do those things? What needs are you trying to fufill? Are those needs being
satiated? As you consciously meet your needs, you will be satiated.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-yield ways to increase happiness</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-11-high-yield-ways-to-increase-happiness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-11-high-yield-ways-to-increase-happiness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The advertising industry usually tries to tell you that if you buy their&#xA;product or service, you will be happy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The problem with this approach to buying happiness is that the increase in&#xA;happiness that you get from buying something will usually attenuate after a&#xA;short period of time.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, there are more effective, longer-lasting ways to increase&#xA;happiness. They just aren&amp;rsquo;t being marketed to you because there&amp;rsquo;s no money in&#xA;them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The advertising industry usually tries to tell you that if you buy their
product or service, you will be happy.</p>
<p>The problem with this approach to buying happiness is that the increase in
happiness that you get from buying something will usually attenuate after a
short period of time.</p>
<p>Fortunately, there are more effective, longer-lasting ways to increase
happiness. They just aren&rsquo;t being marketed to you because there&rsquo;s no money in
them.</p>
<h2 id="decrease-annoyances">Decrease annoyances</h2>
<p>My favorite way to improve life happiness in the long-term is to fix things that
bother me. If you&rsquo;re bothered about twice a week by your gate being stuck when
you want to take out the trash (as I was), it&rsquo;s kind of a no-brainer to take an
hour to diagnose and fix the problem.</p>
<p>This principle can be applied to a wide variety of annoyances. Traffic during a
morning commute. Having to make yourself breakfast every morning. An
inconvenient location for a tool that gets used regularly.</p>
<p>There are probably dozens of inconveniences and frustrations that you deal with
every day, and it&rsquo;s probably worth more than you think to eliminate those daily
annoyances. As you spend less and less of your day being annoyed, you&rsquo;ll be
happier and more productive. Your interpersonal relationships might also
improve, as you&rsquo;ll have more emotional bandwidth for dealing with interpersonal
frictions.</p>
<h2 id="build-in-recurring-pleasures-that-don-t-saturate">Build in recurring pleasures that don&rsquo;t saturate</h2>
<p>Try to find things that you know you can get excited about every day. For me, I
will always get excited about a good meal when I&rsquo;m hungry, so I try to make sure
that my meals can be a regular source of happiness in my day. I do that by
choosing high-quality ingredients and making meals that will make me happy, not
just fill my stomach.</p>
<p>Whatever it is that can make you happy (and not just entertained) every single
time, try to build it into your daily routine. Have a few, regularly-occurring
bright spots you can look forward to each day. It will increase your average
daily happiness in the long run.</p>
<h2 id="think-in-happier-ways">Think in happier ways</h2>
<p>Happiness is a mental and emotional state. One of the most significant, but
difficult things you can do for your happiness is to try to cultivate mental and
emotional habits that facilitate happiness.</p>
<p>This is a complicated topic. It touches on mental illness and the limits of our
ability to control our own thoughts. For now, I think it suffices to say that
it&rsquo;s often possible to change the way that you think in a way that improves your
happiness. There are many frameworks for doing so.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lean into it</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-08-lean-into-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-08-lean-into-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the absence of strong preferences, default to specialization in the ways that&#xA;are most accessible to you.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is a good heuristic because it leverages the random details of your&#xA;circumstances into the possibility of a significant comparative advantage.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I think the world needs more people who are willing to &amp;ldquo;lean into&amp;rdquo; the quirks of&#xA;their individual circumstances. Diversity and specialization are engines of&#xA;scientific progress, economic growth, and artistic expression.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the absence of strong preferences, default to specialization in the ways that
are most accessible to you.</p>
<p>This is a good heuristic because it leverages the random details of your
circumstances into the possibility of a significant comparative advantage.</p>
<p>I think the world needs more people who are willing to &ldquo;lean into&rdquo; the quirks of
their individual circumstances. Diversity and specialization are engines of
scientific progress, economic growth, and artistic expression.</p>
<p>By &ldquo;leaning into it&rdquo; you attempt to take advantage of your unique position,
whatever it is.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I fixed some chairs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-03-i-fixed-some-chairs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-03-i-fixed-some-chairs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I fixed some chairs and it was the most satisfying thing I did all day.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My wife bought some used chairs yesterday, and she noticed after bringing them&#xA;home that they were a little wobbly. This evening, I pulled out my tools and&#xA;started tightening screws to see if I could fix the problem.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the process, I discovered that one of the chairs had been put together&#xA;incorrectly, with two of the legs having been swapped. Because it&#xA;was put together wrong, it was very wobbly and some of the pieces were jammed&#xA;together at crooked angles.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today I fixed some chairs and it was the most satisfying thing I did all day.</p>
<p>My wife bought some used chairs yesterday, and she noticed after bringing them
home that they were a little wobbly. This evening, I pulled out my tools and
started tightening screws to see if I could fix the problem.</p>
<p>In the process, I discovered that one of the chairs had been put together
incorrectly, with two of the legs having been swapped. Because it
was put together wrong, it was very wobbly and some of the pieces were jammed
together at crooked angles.</p>
<p>Being able to sit down with a set of tools, diagnose a problem, and make the
world a better place in just half an hour is a wonderful thing to experience. It
wasn&rsquo;t a big fix, but it greatly improves the experience of sitting in those
chairs.</p>
<p>I think everybody needs moments like this. Everyone needs to experience
regularly the satisfaction of problem-solving on a short timescale. Most of the
things I do on a daily basis do not give me immediate rewards, and that makes it
important that I find things that do give me immediate satisfaction&mdash;running,
cooking, and playing with my daughter are examples that come to mind.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
