<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Joshua Rasband&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Joshua Rasband&#39;s blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <managingEditor>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</webMaster>
    <copyright>Joshua Rasband (CC BY 4.0)</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Reasons being a parent is awesome</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-02-reasons-being-a-parent-is-awesome/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-02-reasons-being-a-parent-is-awesome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I want to share some of the reasons being a parent has been (somewhat&#xA;unexpectedly) so good for me personally. I think these reasons will apply to&#xA;almost every parent.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Before I start, I want to make it clear my goal is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to convince everyone to&#xA;have kids, but rather to show that parenthood is awesome in a couple of ways&#xA;that I don&amp;rsquo;t think get talked about enough.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I want to share some of the reasons being a parent has been (somewhat
unexpectedly) so good for me personally. I think these reasons will apply to
almost every parent.</p>
<p>Before I start, I want to make it clear my goal is <em>not</em> to convince everyone to
have kids, but rather to show that parenthood is awesome in a couple of ways
that I don&rsquo;t think get talked about enough.</p>
<h2 id="being-your-child-s-parent-has-limited--or-no--competition">Being <em>your</em> child&rsquo;s parent has limited (or no) competition</h2>
<p>Competition to be your child&rsquo;s best parent is extremely limited. Unlike your
professional interests (and likely your hobbies), the odds are pretty good that
the pool of people trying to parent <em>your child specifically</em> is small. Sometimes,
it might be a pool of one. I certainly feel that I&rsquo;m only competing against
myself&mdash;that my wife and I occupy different, non-competitive niches in our
daughter&rsquo;s life. Within my niche, I am number one; undefeated! It doesn&rsquo;t matter
to me that there isn&rsquo;t really anyone I&rsquo;m competing against&mdash;it still gives me
satisfaction to know that I am the best at what I do.</p>
<p>Furthermore, whatever you do for your child is going to be a large fraction of
their life experience. It doesn&rsquo;t matter very much if the things you do for them
are imperfect&mdash;what matters more is that you try. Just trying can get you to
the top of the leaderboard&mdash;but you have to try.</p>
<h2 id="being-a-parent-is-orthogonal-to-other-interests">Being a parent is orthogonal to other interests</h2>
<p>How good of a parent you are can be completely uncorrelated with your
professional success, your financial situation, or your hobbies. This
decorrelation between parenting and the rest of your life makes it easier to
still feel like a success, even if the only thing you&rsquo;re succeeding in is being
a good parent to your child.</p>
<h2 id="being-a-parent-is-a-great-mix-of-instant-and-delayed-gratification">Being a parent is a great mix of instant and delayed gratification</h2>
<p>There are two kinds of work&mdash;work that has instantaneous rewards, and work that
has delayed rewards. In my experience, optimal productivity and happiness in
one&rsquo;s work requires a mix of both kinds of work.</p>
<p>Working without any short-term feedback on how you&rsquo;re doing makes it difficult
to improve. Also, a lack of short-term rewards in your work will make each day
exhausting, because at the end of each day you can be left thinking &ldquo;What did I
do all that work today for?&rdquo;</p>
<p>On the other hand, work that only has short-term rewards will never build up to
a lifetime of achievement that you can look back on with satisfaction. You might
be happy on each individual day, but the overall narrative arc is missing.</p>
<p>Parenting, in my opinion, has the perfect mix of short-term and long-term
rewards. In the short-term, it is generally rewarding to spend any amount of
time with your kids doing something they enjoy. In the long-term, the things you
work to teach them (both knowledge and values) can gradually shape your child
into a fully-fledged human that you are happy to associate with.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning by boundary seeking</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-01-learning-by-boundary-seeking/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-01-learning-by-boundary-seeking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last year since I became a parent, I&amp;rsquo;ve had the wonderful opportunity to&#xA;observe how my daughter acquires new skills and learns about the world around&#xA;her.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Boundary seeking&amp;rdquo; is how I think of her main strategy for learning efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When she first encounters a new object, she pushes it to its limits. One day&#xA;last month she found a tote bag and played with it for the better part of an&#xA;hour. She dragged it around the room, she whipped it around her body as fast as&#xA;she could, she put her toys into it, she stepped on it, and of course, she put&#xA;it on her head, which she thought was hilarious. (Don&amp;rsquo;t worry, the tote bag is made from a&#xA;breathable mesh and she was totally supervised the whole time.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the last year since I became a parent, I&rsquo;ve had the wonderful opportunity to
observe how my daughter acquires new skills and learns about the world around
her.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Boundary seeking&rdquo; is how I think of her main strategy for learning efficiently.</p>
<p>When she first encounters a new object, she pushes it to its limits. One day
last month she found a tote bag and played with it for the better part of an
hour. She dragged it around the room, she whipped it around her body as fast as
she could, she put her toys into it, she stepped on it, and of course, she put
it on her head, which she thought was hilarious. (Don&rsquo;t worry, the tote bag is made from a
breathable mesh and she was totally supervised the whole time.)</p>
<p>By sampling over a large distribution space, she was able to find the most
interesting things that she could do with the tote bag. She got lots of
information about the way that the tote bag behaves under a wide variety of
conditions. As she discovered new, interesting behaviors (like putting the bag
over her head) she spend more time exploring them.</p>
<p>This is a very efficient way to learn. Essentially, you sample as big a space as
you can, then focus on the areas of that space that are most interesting to you.
My theory is that these &ldquo;interesting&rdquo; areas of the space represent boundaries on
a manifold, where one behavior changes into another. (Think, for example, about
how the bag might be good for carrying things when you carry it loosely, but
when you swing it around your head it makes a <em>whooshing</em> noise and it&rsquo;s more
fun.) The most efficient way to explore a high-dimensional space is to move
along boundaries, then use simple predictive heuristics to fill in the gaps
between boundaries.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book review: Poor Charlie&#39;s Almanac</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-09-30-book-review-poor-charlies-almanac/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-09-30-book-review-poor-charlies-almanac/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Poor Charlie&amp;rsquo;s Almanac is a collection of talks and essays by Charles Munger,&#xA;who together with Warren Buffett established Berkshire Hathaway as one of the&#xA;greatest investment funds of all time. The talks cover topics from accounting&#xA;practices to the role of psychology in business to general life advice for&#xA;finding happiness.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why you should read this book:&lt;/strong&gt; It&amp;rsquo;s fun to read and has good life advice. This&#xA;book exposes you to the mental models of a highly successful person. For me, the&#xA;biggest takeaway was the framework of &amp;ldquo;mental models&amp;rdquo; itself! I knew about&#xA;mental models, of course, but I had never thought specifically about the idea&#xA;that a collection of mental models of how the world works might serve as a&#xA;general-purpose system for problem-solving and understanding the world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Poor Charlie&rsquo;s Almanac is a collection of talks and essays by Charles Munger,
who together with Warren Buffett established Berkshire Hathaway as one of the
greatest investment funds of all time. The talks cover topics from accounting
practices to the role of psychology in business to general life advice for
finding happiness.</p>
<p><strong>Why you should read this book:</strong> It&rsquo;s fun to read and has good life advice. This
book exposes you to the mental models of a highly successful person. For me, the
biggest takeaway was the framework of &ldquo;mental models&rdquo; itself! I knew about
mental models, of course, but I had never thought specifically about the idea
that a collection of mental models of how the world works might serve as a
general-purpose system for problem-solving and understanding the world.</p>
<p><strong>Why you should not read this book:</strong> If you&rsquo;re looking for specific, quantitative,
actionable investment advice, this is not the right book for you. I&rsquo;m sure that
Buffett and Munger have plenty of quantitative ways that they analyze their
investments, but this is not that kind of book. This is a book that gives a
window into the author&rsquo;s philosophy and worldview.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Against additive solutions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-09-29-against-additive-solutions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-09-29-against-additive-solutions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was recently in a meeting where, multiple times, the default response to a&#xA;problem was &amp;ldquo;we should form a committee to respond to the issue&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;someone&#xA;should be appointed to take care of this issue.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I think this is a natural way to view problems and solutions. It&amp;rsquo;s a&#xA;human-centric view. In this view, problems get solved by people. When some&#xA;problem isn&amp;rsquo;t getting solved because it&amp;rsquo;s not in anyone&amp;rsquo;s job description to&#xA;solve the problem, the logical response is to either delegate authority and&#xA;responsibility for solving the problem to a person or a committee.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I was recently in a meeting where, multiple times, the default response to a
problem was &ldquo;we should form a committee to respond to the issue&rdquo; or &ldquo;someone
should be appointed to take care of this issue.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I think this is a natural way to view problems and solutions. It&rsquo;s a
human-centric view. In this view, problems get solved by people. When some
problem isn&rsquo;t getting solved because it&rsquo;s not in anyone&rsquo;s job description to
solve the problem, the logical response is to either delegate authority and
responsibility for solving the problem to a person or a committee.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a natural way to view problem-solving in organizations, but it&rsquo;s totally
wrong.</p>
<p>The first reason it&rsquo;s wrong is because it&rsquo;s what I call an &ldquo;additive&rdquo; solution.
The proposed solutions (forming a committee or appointing someone to address the
problem) will either add to the headcount of your organization or they will add
to the demands on people already at your organization.</p>
<p>What&rsquo;s so bad about additive solutions? It has to do with being able to predict
the downstream effects of the implemented solution. There is a fundamental
difference between a solution that involves adding a new component to a system,
versus a solution that takes away or modifies components that were already
there. When you add a new component, it&rsquo;s very difficult to anticipate all the
interactions that it will have with other components. In contrast, when you
modify or remove existing components, it&rsquo;s much easier to anticipate the
consequences by examining the role the component already plays in the system.</p>
<p>Additive solutions are slow. Creating a new component for your system is almost
certainly going to take more time than tweaking (or removing) something that&rsquo;s
already there. When starting from scratch, the design space is huge. In
constrast, when you&rsquo;re starting from an existing part, its attributes are mostly
fixed and you can think about a few dimensions that might need modification. At
the most extreme, you can decide to remove the component, which can be done
incredibly quickly.</p>
<p>Additive solutions are difficult to unwind. One a committee has been formed or a
person given a new responsibility, it is very difficult to turn back the clock,
even after the problem has been solved.</p>
<p>What&rsquo;s the alternative to additive solutions? Solutions that either modify or
remove existing components of the system. In my opinion, this is the most
effective way to solve problems because the problems are usually the result of
interactions of existing system components. Instead of adding downstream
components to solve problems that were introduced previously, why not go
upstream and prevent the problem from occurring in the first place?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing and worth</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-09-28-testing-and-worth/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-09-28-testing-and-worth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In standardized education the primary purpose of an exam is to measure how much&#xA;a student is &amp;ldquo;worth.&amp;rdquo; This is wrong. The primary purpose of an exam should be to&#xA;determine what the student knows.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What is it that people do with exam grades? They use them to compare students&#xA;against each other, as a way to determine which students are &amp;ldquo;better&amp;rdquo; than other&#xA;students. A grade serves much the same function as a price in a marketplace&amp;mdash;it&#xA;abstracts away all of the details until you have a single number that you can&#xA;use to compare unlike things. Grades are one of the primary metrics for&#xA;determining whether a student will be admitted to a university, admitted to a&#xA;doctoral program, or offered an internship or job. The primary purpose of exam&#xA;grades is therefore to determine which students are &amp;ldquo;better&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;worse&amp;rdquo; than&#xA;others, because that is how people use grades.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In standardized education the primary purpose of an exam is to measure how much
a student is &ldquo;worth.&rdquo; This is wrong. The primary purpose of an exam should be to
determine what the student knows.</p>
<p>What is it that people do with exam grades? They use them to compare students
against each other, as a way to determine which students are &ldquo;better&rdquo; than other
students. A grade serves much the same function as a price in a marketplace&mdash;it
abstracts away all of the details until you have a single number that you can
use to compare unlike things. Grades are one of the primary metrics for
determining whether a student will be admitted to a university, admitted to a
doctoral program, or offered an internship or job. The primary purpose of exam
grades is therefore to determine which students are &ldquo;better&rdquo; or &ldquo;worse&rdquo; than
others, because that is how people use grades.</p>
<p>I think it&rsquo;s wrong to abstract away all information about a student&rsquo;s knowledge
until all that is left is a single, crude numeric measure. When a teacher (or a
student) sees a grade, it is an extremely imprecise error signal.</p>
<p>The purpose of teaching is learning, and learning is better served by a precise
error signal, one which gives the student and the teacher feedback about what
the student does know and what the student doesn&rsquo;t know. Exams and grading must
be structured so that they are a measure of knowledge and knowledge gaps. Until
then, exams will be a measure of &ldquo;worth,&rdquo; and students who do poorly on exams
will view themselves as being unworthy or less valuable when they instead should
view themselves as just not knowing something yet.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time to write</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-09-27-time-to-write/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-09-27-time-to-write/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If writing down your ideas always makes them more precise and more complete,&#xA;then no one who hasn&amp;rsquo;t written about a topic has fully formed ideas about it.&#xA;And someone who never writes has no fully formed ideas about anything&#xA;nontrivial.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash;Paul Graham&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I think that the next phase of my self-education is writing. Here&amp;rsquo;s why:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing generates an error signal:&lt;/strong&gt; Writing externalizes your thought process,&#xA;which makes it easier to reflect on which of your thoughts need to improve.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>If writing down your ideas always makes them more precise and more complete,
then no one who hasn&rsquo;t written about a topic has fully formed ideas about it.
And someone who never writes has no fully formed ideas about anything
nontrivial.</p>
<p>&mdash;Paul Graham</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think that the next phase of my self-education is writing. Here&rsquo;s why:</p>
<p><strong>Writing generates an error signal:</strong> Writing externalizes your thought process,
which makes it easier to reflect on which of your thoughts need to improve.</p>
<p><strong>Writing is a form of retrieval practice:</strong> Retrieval practice is the best
known technique for building and strengthening long-term memory.</p>
<p>These two factors make writing a highly efficient learning technique.</p>
<p>Because I&rsquo;ve previously had a hard time writing consistently, I&rsquo;m making a
commitment: for the next month (until October 27th, 2024), I will write one blog
post every day. They probably won&rsquo;t be very long (or very good), but I&rsquo;m going to
write them.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;MD/PhD student in the United States&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Currently working on a neuroscience PhD&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jrasband/&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9548-7311&#34;&gt;ORCID&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/JoshuaRasband&#34;&gt;X (Twitter)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<ul>
<li>MD/PhD student in the United States</li>
<li>Currently working on a neuroscience PhD</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/jrasband/">github</a></li>
<li><a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9548-7311">ORCID</a></li>
<li><a href="https://x.com/JoshuaRasband">X (Twitter)</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
