<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Joshua Rasband&#39;s website</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Joshua Rasband&#39;s website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <managingEditor>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</webMaster>
    <copyright>Joshua Rasband (CC BY 4.0)</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Better is better than more</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-23-better-is-better-than-more/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-23-better-is-better-than-more/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most of the time, when I say &amp;ldquo;I should be doing more&amp;rdquo; what I &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be saying is&#xA;&amp;ldquo;I should be doing things differently.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s often assumed that we could always be doing &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt;. Exercising more, sleeping&#xA;more, working more, reading more… more, more, more. I&amp;rsquo;m not convinced that&amp;rsquo;s&#xA;true.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are 24 hours in a day, and we spend each minute of the day doing&#xA;&lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;. We&amp;rsquo;re never going to be able to fit more than 24 hours of time into a&#xA;day. The task left to us is to determine &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; we&amp;rsquo;re going to use the time we&#xA;have.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Most of the time, when I say &ldquo;I should be doing more&rdquo; what I <em>should</em> be saying is
&ldquo;I should be doing things differently.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s often assumed that we could always be doing <em>more</em>. Exercising more, sleeping
more, working more, reading more… more, more, more. I&rsquo;m not convinced that&rsquo;s
true.</p>
<p>There are 24 hours in a day, and we spend each minute of the day doing
<em>something</em>. We&rsquo;re never going to be able to fit more than 24 hours of time into a
day. The task left to us is to determine <em>how</em> we&rsquo;re going to use the time we
have.</p>
<p>Why is this distinction important? Psychologically, it can be daunting to think
about adding things to our to-do list without taking anything away. I&rsquo;ve found
it&rsquo;s helpful to think about how I should be doing things better rather than how
I should be doing more.</p>
<p>My success rate for behavioral modification improves when I&rsquo;m able to identify
how existing components of my daily life will be modified or replaced by
something better. Instead of planning to complete a task at a vague
&ldquo;sometime,&rdquo; I can identify a specific time of day at which I will change my
behavior from what was previously planned. This dramatically increases my
chances of success.</p>
<p>This principle also applies in large organizations and bureaucracies. Better is
superior to more.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introductory CS education misses the useful stuff</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-18-introductory-cs-education-misses-the-useful-stuff/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-18-introductory-cs-education-misses-the-useful-stuff/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The most important things I&amp;rsquo;ve learned about how to use a computer were things&#xA;that I&amp;rsquo;ve had to teach myself.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My formal CS education consists of an AP class in high school, an&#xA;introductory-level CS class in college, and three computational physics labs. In&#xA;none of those classes did I learn about shell scripting, version control, or&#xA;package management.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Together, these three skills have opened up worlds of&#xA;productivity and possibility for me. They gave me the ability to write quick&#xA;scripts to move and rename files &lt;em&gt;en masse&lt;/em&gt;, improved how I fix bugs and implement&#xA;features, and gave me access to a huge ecosystem of publicly available tools.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The most important things I&rsquo;ve learned about how to use a computer were things
that I&rsquo;ve had to teach myself.</p>
<p>My formal CS education consists of an AP class in high school, an
introductory-level CS class in college, and three computational physics labs. In
none of those classes did I learn about shell scripting, version control, or
package management.</p>
<p>Together, these three skills have opened up worlds of
productivity and possibility for me. They gave me the ability to write quick
scripts to move and rename files <em>en masse</em>, improved how I fix bugs and implement
features, and gave me access to a huge ecosystem of publicly available tools.</p>
<p>I think it&rsquo;s likely that this observation applies to formal education generally.
Rather than starting with the most useful things, formal education usually
starts with some theoretical fundamentals which are supposed to build up to
something useful (think &ldquo;the mitochondria is the powerhouse of the cell&rdquo;). Maybe
we need to consider inverting that structure, so that students first learn how
to do useful things, and then they can learn the foundational knowledge they&rsquo;ll
need as they want to improve their skills.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deliberate practice of self-mastery</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-17-deliberate-practice-of-self-mastery/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-17-deliberate-practice-of-self-mastery/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The single most important factor for success is having self-mastery.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Self-mastery is difficult to teach, but it can be cultivated. The key is to&#xA;developing self-mastery is proper stewardship of the reward circuits of your&#xA;brain. You need to make sure that your brain sends reward signal in ways that&#xA;will direct you to achieve your goals.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The main way that I have accomplished this is through deliberate practice. Every&#xA;time I want some kind of reward or break, I push myself to work just a little&#xA;longer before I reward myself. Then, when I accomplish my goal, the sense of&#xA;reward is associated with self-mastery, rather than giving in, thereby&#xA;reinforcing a sense of pleasure at delayed gratification.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The single most important factor for success is having self-mastery.</p>
<p>Self-mastery is difficult to teach, but it can be cultivated. The key is to
developing self-mastery is proper stewardship of the reward circuits of your
brain. You need to make sure that your brain sends reward signal in ways that
will direct you to achieve your goals.</p>
<p>The main way that I have accomplished this is through deliberate practice. Every
time I want some kind of reward or break, I push myself to work just a little
longer before I reward myself. Then, when I accomplish my goal, the sense of
reward is associated with self-mastery, rather than giving in, thereby
reinforcing a sense of pleasure at delayed gratification.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m now at a point where a lot of the pleasure in my day comes from the
knowledge that I have successfully achieved my goals. On nights when I force
myself to do the dishes and finish my homework before I let myself have dessert,
it&rsquo;s the sense of accomplishment that is the bigger reward.</p>
<p>This is a difficult pattern of thought to cultivate. It&rsquo;s taken me almost a
decade to get here. The rewards are enormous, however. The ability to say no to
basically any distraction or temptation in favor of accomplishing my goals has
been of critical importance as I try to balance my many responsibilities and
goals.</p>
<p>As a final note, self-mastery does not have to mean that every waking moment is
spent working or studying. It just means that your decisions are more fully
yours. I have found that self-mastery has actually increased my enjoyment of
leisure activities, because I can engage in them with the knowledge that I have
picked leisure because it is what I want to do, not because it is easy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Values vs. tastes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-15-values-vs-tastes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-15-values-vs-tastes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After I got married, I learned an important lesson: there is a big difference&#xA;between differences in taste and differences in values. Differences in taste are&#xA;easy to live with and usually easy to compromise on. Differences in values are&#xA;basically impossible to come to a satisfactory compromise on. The way you like&#xA;your scrambled eggs is a taste. Whether you think it&amp;rsquo;s morally justified to be&#xA;eating eggs at all is a value.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>After I got married, I learned an important lesson: there is a big difference
between differences in taste and differences in values. Differences in taste are
easy to live with and usually easy to compromise on. Differences in values are
basically impossible to come to a satisfactory compromise on. The way you like
your scrambled eggs is a taste. Whether you think it&rsquo;s morally justified to be
eating eggs at all is a value.</p>
<p>What&rsquo;s the difference between a taste and a value? I think a taste is basically
a personal preference which you recognize is not intrinsically superior to other
preferences. In contrast, a value is something that you believe in because you
view it as being better or more true than other, competing values. Values are
not viewed as a matter of preference, which makes them more difficult to
compromise on.</p>
<p>Although it&rsquo;s much more difficult to find compromise when there&rsquo;s a difference
of values, a values-centered discussion can be very meaningful and productive.
It&rsquo;s very much possible to have one set of values, yet respect deeply another
person&rsquo;s commitment to a different set of values. Values are also typically not
a choice between right and wrong, but a choice between many good options, one of
which is deemed most important. When you understand someone at the level of
their values, you gain far more insight into their reasoning than if you were to
understand them at a more superficial level.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Find joys that satiate you</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-14-find-joys-that-satiate-you/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-14-find-joys-that-satiate-you/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some activities are &amp;lsquo;satiating&amp;rsquo;&amp;mdash;when you&amp;rsquo;re done, you don&amp;rsquo;t have an increased&#xA;desire to do or consume more. Think about a meal that leaves your hunger totally&#xA;satisfied. That kind of a pleasure is the kind of pleasure that we ought to be&#xA;spending most of our time on, in contrast to things that, like potato chips, never&#xA;satisfy the desire they were supposed to address in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many modern forms of entertainment, such as social media and streaming&#xA;television, don&amp;rsquo;t satiate. As a result, people spend much more time consuming&#xA;than they intend to. To continue the analogy, they wanted to satisfy their&#xA;hunger, but instead of eating a meal, they opened up a bag of potato chips.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some activities are &lsquo;satiating&rsquo;&mdash;when you&rsquo;re done, you don&rsquo;t have an increased
desire to do or consume more. Think about a meal that leaves your hunger totally
satisfied. That kind of a pleasure is the kind of pleasure that we ought to be
spending most of our time on, in contrast to things that, like potato chips, never
satisfy the desire they were supposed to address in the first place.</p>
<p>Many modern forms of entertainment, such as social media and streaming
television, don&rsquo;t satiate. As a result, people spend much more time consuming
than they intend to. To continue the analogy, they wanted to satisfy their
hunger, but instead of eating a meal, they opened up a bag of potato chips.</p>
<p>Look at your day and think about the things that you spend time doing. Why do
you do those things? What needs are you trying to fufill? Are those needs being
satiated? As you consciously meet your needs, you will be satiated.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why I make my own flashcards</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-12-why-i-make-my-own-flashcards/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-12-why-i-make-my-own-flashcards/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During medical school, I started using the Anki spaced repetition system to put&#xA;large amounts of knowledge into my long-term memory. At first, I used decks made&#xA;by other students. Eventually, I found that I preferred creating my own&#xA;flashcards over using decks of pre-made flashcards.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;focus&#34;&gt;Focus&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Making my own flashcards is a significant use of time and effort. At first&#xA;blush, that sounds like it&amp;rsquo;s a disadvantage, but it can also be framed as a&#xA;benefit. Because there is a non-zero cost to making my flashcards, it&#xA;incentivizes me to make the minimum number of flashcards necessary and no more.&#xA;I found that before I started making my own cards, I was tempted to download&#xA;more decks than I reasonably had time to study. The cost incurred by making my&#xA;own cards helps me foucs my energies on just the facts that I want to remember.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>During medical school, I started using the Anki spaced repetition system to put
large amounts of knowledge into my long-term memory. At first, I used decks made
by other students. Eventually, I found that I preferred creating my own
flashcards over using decks of pre-made flashcards.</p>
<h2 id="focus">Focus</h2>
<p>Making my own flashcards is a significant use of time and effort. At first
blush, that sounds like it&rsquo;s a disadvantage, but it can also be framed as a
benefit. Because there is a non-zero cost to making my flashcards, it
incentivizes me to make the minimum number of flashcards necessary and no more.
I found that before I started making my own cards, I was tempted to download
more decks than I reasonably had time to study. The cost incurred by making my
own cards helps me foucs my energies on just the facts that I want to remember.</p>
<h2 id="ownership">Ownership</h2>
<p>Because I make my own flashcards, I have a deeper sense of accountability for my
study. When I see a &ldquo;bad&rdquo; flashcard (e.g. one that is poorly worded or
ambiguous) I know that it&rsquo;s my fault and I need to fix it. When using a deck
made by someone else, it&rsquo;s easier to ignore the card and keep studying without
improving anything. The knowledge that my flashcards are fully my responsibility
helps me keep iterating and making better and better cards.</p>
<h2 id="schema-construction">Schema construction</h2>
<p>The process of making flashcards helps me construct a schema into which I can
place facts. When I make flashcards, I have to ask myself what the most
important things to know are. As I organize my notes, it encourages me to think
about the relationships between concepts&mdash;how they are similar, how they are
different. By making flashcards, I give myself time to think about the facts I&rsquo;m
studying and how they are related&mdash;something I wouldn&rsquo;t be forced to do if I
were to rely soley on decks made by other people.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-yield ways to increase happiness</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-11-high-yield-ways-to-increase-happiness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-11-high-yield-ways-to-increase-happiness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The advertising industry usually tries to tell you that if you buy their&#xA;product or service, you will be happy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The problem with this approach to buying happiness is that the increase in&#xA;happiness that you get from buying something will usually attenuate after a&#xA;short period of time.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, there are more effective, longer-lasting ways to increase&#xA;happiness. They just aren&amp;rsquo;t being marketed to you because there&amp;rsquo;s no money in&#xA;them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The advertising industry usually tries to tell you that if you buy their
product or service, you will be happy.</p>
<p>The problem with this approach to buying happiness is that the increase in
happiness that you get from buying something will usually attenuate after a
short period of time.</p>
<p>Fortunately, there are more effective, longer-lasting ways to increase
happiness. They just aren&rsquo;t being marketed to you because there&rsquo;s no money in
them.</p>
<h2 id="decrease-annoyances">Decrease annoyances</h2>
<p>My favorite way to improve life happiness in the long-term is to fix things that
bother me. If you&rsquo;re bothered about twice a week by your gate being stuck when
you want to take out the trash (as I was), it&rsquo;s kind of a no-brainer to take an
hour to diagnose and fix the problem.</p>
<p>This principle can be applied to a wide variety of annoyances. Traffic during a
morning commute. Having to make yourself breakfast every morning. An
inconvenient location for a tool that gets used regularly.</p>
<p>There are probably dozens of inconveniences and frustrations that you deal with
every day, and it&rsquo;s probably worth more than you think to eliminate those daily
annoyances. As you spend less and less of your day being annoyed, you&rsquo;ll be
happier and more productive. Your interpersonal relationships might also
improve, as you&rsquo;ll have more emotional bandwidth for dealing with interpersonal
frictions.</p>
<h2 id="build-in-recurring-pleasures-that-don-t-saturate">Build in recurring pleasures that don&rsquo;t saturate</h2>
<p>Try to find things that you know you can get excited about every day. For me, I
will always get excited about a good meal when I&rsquo;m hungry, so I try to make sure
that my meals can be a regular source of happiness in my day. I do that by
choosing high-quality ingredients and making meals that will make me happy, not
just fill my stomach.</p>
<p>Whatever it is that can make you happy (and not just entertained) every single
time, try to build it into your daily routine. Have a few, regularly-occurring
bright spots you can look forward to each day. It will increase your average
daily happiness in the long run.</p>
<h2 id="think-in-happier-ways">Think in happier ways</h2>
<p>Happiness is a mental and emotional state. One of the most significant, but
difficult things you can do for your happiness is to try to cultivate mental and
emotional habits that facilitate happiness.</p>
<p>This is a complicated topic. It touches on mental illness and the limits of our
ability to control our own thoughts. For now, I think it suffices to say that
it&rsquo;s often possible to change the way that you think in a way that improves your
happiness. There are many frameworks for doing so.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An overview of my Emacs journey</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-10-an-overview-of-my-emacs-journey/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-10-an-overview-of-my-emacs-journey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll probably write more about the ways that Emacs (and Org mode) has improved&#xA;my life, but here&amp;rsquo;s a brief summary.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I started using Emacs during college after getting introduced to Org mode by my&#xA;research mentor. I&amp;rsquo;d just gotten burned by two of my preferred software tools&#xA;getting shut down&amp;mdash;one was a text editor, and the other was a productivity&#xA;manager, so I was about as receptive as one could be to the idea of open-source&#xA;text editors and productivity managers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ll probably write more about the ways that Emacs (and Org mode) has improved
my life, but here&rsquo;s a brief summary.</p>
<p>I started using Emacs during college after getting introduced to Org mode by my
research mentor. I&rsquo;d just gotten burned by two of my preferred software tools
getting shut down&mdash;one was a text editor, and the other was a productivity
manager, so I was about as receptive as one could be to the idea of open-source
text editors and productivity managers.</p>
<p>Over the next few years, Emacs became an integral part of my writing,
note-taking, and programming workflows. Part of what I enjoyed about Emacs was
how it challenged me to learn more and to become more. Emacs didn&rsquo;t hold my
hand&mdash;it demanded that I learn how to program.</p>
<p>Another key component was the community. Without the abundance of blogs and
forums and YouTube tutorials guiding me at each step of my Emacs path, I
probably would have given up early on. The thing that I loved the most about the
Emacs (and computer science community in general) is that they seemed to be the
kind of people I wanted to be around. They were curious, hard-working, and
clever. They had interesting ideas and interesting taste.</p>
<p>Now, I&rsquo;m a committed Emacs user. It&rsquo;s not for everyone, but I love how it&rsquo;s
helped me grow, I love the ideas and communities it&rsquo;s helped me discover, and I
love the sense of ownership and independence that open source brings me.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved org-capture on MacOS</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-09-improved-org-capture-on-macos/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-09-improved-org-capture-on-macos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I read &lt;a href=&#34;https://macowners.club/posts/org-capture-from-everywhere-macos/&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; and it got me excited about using &lt;code&gt;emacsclient&lt;/code&gt; to capture from&#xA;anywhere on MacOS. I was particular about getting the capture frame to show only&#xA;capture-related buffers, so I needed to make some modifications to the original&#xA;code based on comments on &lt;a href=&#34;https://emacs.stackexchange.com/questions/46460/org-capture-frame-with-no-splits&#34;&gt;this stackoverflow question&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my solution:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-text&#34; data-lang=&#34;text&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt; 1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;(defun my/make-org-capture-frame ()&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt; 2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &amp;#34;Create a new frame and run `org-capture&amp;#39;.&amp;#34;&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt; 3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  (interactive)&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt; 4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  (make-frame &amp;#39;((name . &amp;#34;capture&amp;#34;)&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt; 5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;                (top . 300)&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt; 6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;                (left . 700)&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt; 7&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;                (width . 80)&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt; 8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;                (height . 25)))&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt; 9&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  (select-frame-by-name &amp;#34;capture&amp;#34;)&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  (delete-other-windows)&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  (cl-letf (((symbol-function &amp;#39;switch-to-buffer-other-window) #&amp;#39;switch-to-buffer) ((symbol-function &amp;#39;org-display-buffer-split) #&amp;#39;org-display-buffer-full-frame)) (org-capture)))&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;(defun my/org-capture-delete-frame (orig-fun &amp;amp;rest args)&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  (if (equal &amp;#34;capture&amp;#34; (frame-parameter nil &amp;#39;name))&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      (delete-frame))&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  (apply orig-fun args))&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt;17&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;(advice-add &amp;#39;user-error :around #&amp;#39;my/org-capture-delete-frame)&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt;19&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;(advice-add &amp;#39;org-capture-finalize :around #&amp;#39;my/org-capture-delete-frame)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now you can call &lt;code&gt;emacsclient -nw --eval &amp;quot;(my/make-org-capture-frame)&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; and it&#xA;will open a capture buffer in a new frame.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I read <a href="https://macowners.club/posts/org-capture-from-everywhere-macos/">this post</a> and it got me excited about using <code>emacsclient</code> to capture from
anywhere on MacOS. I was particular about getting the capture frame to show only
capture-related buffers, so I needed to make some modifications to the original
code based on comments on <a href="https://emacs.stackexchange.com/questions/46460/org-capture-frame-with-no-splits">this stackoverflow question</a>.</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s my solution:</p>





<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-text" data-lang="text"><span class="line"><span class="ln"> 1</span><span class="cl">(defun my/make-org-capture-frame ()
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="ln"> 2</span><span class="cl">  &#34;Create a new frame and run `org-capture&#39;.&#34;
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="ln"> 3</span><span class="cl">  (interactive)
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="ln"> 4</span><span class="cl">  (make-frame &#39;((name . &#34;capture&#34;)
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="ln"> 5</span><span class="cl">                (top . 300)
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="ln"> 6</span><span class="cl">                (left . 700)
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="ln"> 7</span><span class="cl">                (width . 80)
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="ln"> 8</span><span class="cl">                (height . 25)))
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="ln"> 9</span><span class="cl">  (select-frame-by-name &#34;capture&#34;)
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="ln">10</span><span class="cl">  (delete-other-windows)
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="ln">11</span><span class="cl">  (cl-letf (((symbol-function &#39;switch-to-buffer-other-window) #&#39;switch-to-buffer) ((symbol-function &#39;org-display-buffer-split) #&#39;org-display-buffer-full-frame)) (org-capture)))
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="ln">12</span><span class="cl">
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="ln">13</span><span class="cl">(defun my/org-capture-delete-frame (orig-fun &amp;rest args)
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="ln">14</span><span class="cl">  (if (equal &#34;capture&#34; (frame-parameter nil &#39;name))
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="ln">15</span><span class="cl">      (delete-frame))
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="ln">16</span><span class="cl">  (apply orig-fun args))
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="ln">17</span><span class="cl">
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="ln">18</span><span class="cl">(advice-add &#39;user-error :around #&#39;my/org-capture-delete-frame)
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="ln">19</span><span class="cl">(advice-add &#39;org-capture-finalize :around #&#39;my/org-capture-delete-frame)</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Now you can call <code>emacsclient -nw --eval &quot;(my/make-org-capture-frame)&quot;</code> and it
will open a capture buffer in a new frame.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lean into it</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-08-lean-into-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-08-lean-into-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the absence of strong preferences, default to specialization in the ways that&#xA;are most accessible to you.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is a good heuristic because it leverages the random details of your&#xA;circumstances into the possibility of a significant comparative advantage.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I think the world needs more people who are willing to &amp;ldquo;lean into&amp;rdquo; the quirks of&#xA;their individual circumstances. Diversity and specialization are engines of&#xA;scientific progress, economic growth, and artistic expression.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the absence of strong preferences, default to specialization in the ways that
are most accessible to you.</p>
<p>This is a good heuristic because it leverages the random details of your
circumstances into the possibility of a significant comparative advantage.</p>
<p>I think the world needs more people who are willing to &ldquo;lean into&rdquo; the quirks of
their individual circumstances. Diversity and specialization are engines of
scientific progress, economic growth, and artistic expression.</p>
<p>By &ldquo;leaning into it&rdquo; you attempt to take advantage of your unique position,
whatever it is.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-07-book-review-zen-and-the-art-of-motorcycle-maintenance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-07-book-review-zen-and-the-art-of-motorcycle-maintenance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance&lt;/em&gt; can be thought of as an answer to a&#xA;simple question: what is Good?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The answer is something called &amp;ldquo;Quality.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Quality is a kind of you-know-it-when-you-see-it sort of Goodness that comes&#xA;from authentic ways of working, creating, and being. It&amp;rsquo;s the thing that makes&#xA;me savor &lt;a href=&#34;https:jrasband.com/posts/2024-10-04-the-spiritual-dimension-of-food&#34;&gt;a homemade PB&amp;amp;J&lt;/a&gt; just as much as a restaurant cheeseburger. It&amp;rsquo;s the&#xA;secret sauce, the mojo, the oomph.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance</em> can be thought of as an answer to a
simple question: what is Good?</p>
<p>The answer is something called &ldquo;Quality.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Quality is a kind of you-know-it-when-you-see-it sort of Goodness that comes
from authentic ways of working, creating, and being. It&rsquo;s the thing that makes
me savor <a href="https:jrasband.com/posts/2024-10-04-the-spiritual-dimension-of-food">a homemade PB&amp;J</a> just as much as a restaurant cheeseburger. It&rsquo;s the
secret sauce, the mojo, the oomph.</p>
<p><em>Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance</em> is a book for our time. Everywhere I
look I see a dearth of quality. Technological advances have made it so that
every human activity demands less and less of us, so we give less of ourselves
and get less in return.</p>
<p>This was not a satisfying book to read. Its <em>dramatis personae</em> are in pain. It
asks more questions than it answers. However, it was certainly worth my time.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sabbaths and anti-sabbaths</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-06-sabbaths-and-anti-sabbaths/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-06-sabbaths-and-anti-sabbaths/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How a day dedicated to the profane improves my well-being&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;https://alexanderell.is/posts/infinite-scroll/&#34;&gt;lizard brain&lt;/a&gt; was losing the battle against the internet.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I kept finding interesting things that I just &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to read. I knew from past&#xA;experience that it was unreasonable to attempt quitting reading things on the&#xA;internet altogether. I might &amp;ldquo;get clean&amp;rdquo; for a few days or a few weeks, but&#xA;invariably there would be &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; I felt was worthy reading material and I&amp;rsquo;d&#xA;be back to my old ways. I felt like the optimal amount of time spent reading&#xA;news and blog posts was non-zero, but it also wasn&amp;rsquo;t multiple hours per day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>How a day dedicated to the profane improves my well-being</em></p>
<p>My <a href="https://alexanderell.is/posts/infinite-scroll/">lizard brain</a> was losing the battle against the internet.</p>
<p>I kept finding interesting things that I just <em>had</em> to read. I knew from past
experience that it was unreasonable to attempt quitting reading things on the
internet altogether. I might &ldquo;get clean&rdquo; for a few days or a few weeks, but
invariably there would be <em>something</em> I felt was worthy reading material and I&rsquo;d
be back to my old ways. I felt like the optimal amount of time spent reading
news and blog posts was non-zero, but it also wasn&rsquo;t multiple hours per day.</p>
<p>Eventually I solved my problem by borrowing and inverting an ancient practice:
the Sabbath. In some faiths, the core idea of the Sabbath is that it&rsquo;s a holy
day of rest occurring one day per week, a day not to be profaned by certain
activities such as work, commerce, or recreational pursuits.</p>
<p>However, instead of refraining one day per week from the &ldquo;unholy&rdquo; activities of
reading news and blog posts, I flipped it around: one day per week would be set
aside for these &ldquo;unholy&rdquo; activities, and one day only. I call this day my
&ldquo;anti-Sabbath.&rdquo; I chose mine to be on Friday.</p>
<p>The anti-Sabbath has multiple advantages. First, it&rsquo;s a stronger argument, even
if it&rsquo;s less rational. Why can&rsquo;t I read Scott Alexander&rsquo;s <a href="https://astralcodexten.substack.com/p/every-bay-area-house-party">latest</a> <a href="https://astralcodexten.substack.com/p/another-bay-area-house-party">installment</a> <a href="https://astralcodexten.substack.com/p/even-more-bay-area-house-party">of</a>
&ldquo;Bay Area House Party&rdquo;? Because it&rsquo;s not Friday yet. My old argument against
reading blog posts was mostly an appeal to productivity, which is a much weaker
argument. I could always rationalize that I&rsquo;d really be more productive after a
little break, or that it will be a really fast break and then I&rsquo;ll get back to
work. In contrast, I can&rsquo;t argue very much about which day of the week it is.</p>
<p>Second, the anti-Sabbath helps me be more efficient with my reading. Instead of
spreading my internet browsing out over the course of a week, I have to pack it
into a single day, in addition to all of the other things I already have to do
that day. By the time I get around to reading all the new links in my RSS reader
or checking the top page of HackerNews, I&rsquo;m short on time and I can&rsquo;t afford to
read things that are only slighly interesting to me. I discard links I&rsquo;m not
very interested in, which ends up being about half of what shows up in my RSS
reader. If I start reading something and discover that it&rsquo;s not very good, I&rsquo;ll
stop reading it. Having limited time in which to enjoy the week&rsquo;s news and other
reading helps me use that time effectively.</p>
<p>Third, the anti-Sabbath turns what was once an escape into a chore. Compressing
all of my reading into one evening makes it a far less enjoyable experience than
if I were to spread it out over the course of a week. Making my distraction
reading an unpleasant experience makes it much, much easier to resist on every
other day of the week. This has been great for breaking my habit of compulsively
checking newsfeeds such as HackerNews.</p>
<p>Finally, anti-Sabbaths help alleviate the fear of missing out that I would get
from trying to quit altogether. When I&rsquo;m worried that I could be missing
important events, I can remind myself that really important things will still be
headlines by the end of the week, and the things that don&rsquo;t matter by the end of
the week aren&rsquo;t worth reading at all.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning vs. task completion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-04-learning-vs-task-completion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-04-learning-vs-task-completion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Optimize studying for learning, not task completion.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rote completion of a task is best done by specialization and division of labor.&#xA;The classical example of division of labor is &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Division_of_labour#Adam_Smith&#34;&gt;the making of pins&lt;/a&gt; &amp;mdash; by dividing&#xA;the making of a pin into many simple tasks and assigning a worker to each task,&#xA;pins can be made more efficiently than if every worker were to go through all&#xA;the steps of making a pin.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Optimize studying for learning, not task completion.</p>
<p>Rote completion of a task is best done by specialization and division of labor.
The classical example of division of labor is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Division_of_labour#Adam_Smith">the making of pins</a> &mdash; by dividing
the making of a pin into many simple tasks and assigning a worker to each task,
pins can be made more efficiently than if every worker were to go through all
the steps of making a pin.</p>
<p>In the quest for greater efficiency in my studies, I have fallen into the trap
of specialization of labor. If I&rsquo;ve already watched two or three lectures, I&rsquo;m
in a lecture-watching and note-taking frame of mind. If I&rsquo;m studying with
flashcards, it&rsquo;s easy for me to continue studying with flashcards. When I&rsquo;m &ldquo;in
the zone,&rdquo; the least effortful study task is to continue doing what I&rsquo;m already
doing. This feels more efficient because I&rsquo;m rapidly checking more things off my
to-do list, but it&rsquo;s not the most effective way for me to <em>learn.</em></p>
<p>Learning is not the same as checking tasks off a to-do list. Watching four
lectures instead of one in a single sitting doesn&rsquo;t mean that I&rsquo;ve learned four
times as much. On the contrary, I might experience information overload by
trying to absorb too much information in one sitting.</p>
<p>Learning needs to happen incrementally because new information and memories
decay quickly. Self-testing and reflection shortly after the first exposure help
consolidate ideas for long-term storage. Although task-switching while learning
is less efficient in terms of time used studying in a given day, information
will be better retained.</p>
<p>Learning is the cultivation of an interconnected garden of information and ideas
that live in your brain. Plants don&rsquo;t grow, die, or bear fruit all at once.
Neither do ideas. Effective study requires doing the right study tasks at the
right time, not just as quickly as possible.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-overlapping sources of social support</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-04-non-overlapping-sources-of-social-support/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-04-non-overlapping-sources-of-social-support/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine once advised some first-year medical students to develop&#xA;&lt;em&gt;non-overlapping&lt;/em&gt; sources of social support.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;His line of thinking went like this: if your only source of friends is your&#xA;peers at school or work, you will be dependent on your work for your social&#xA;life. Any disruption to your work would affect your social life, and &lt;em&gt;vice versa&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, socializing with co-workers often constrains conversation to&#xA;work-related topics. This is because people naturally default to the things they&#xA;have in common, which are the things that are easiest to talk about.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A friend of mine once advised some first-year medical students to develop
<em>non-overlapping</em> sources of social support.</p>
<p>His line of thinking went like this: if your only source of friends is your
peers at school or work, you will be dependent on your work for your social
life. Any disruption to your work would affect your social life, and <em>vice versa</em>.</p>
<p>Additionally, socializing with co-workers often constrains conversation to
work-related topics. This is because people naturally default to the things they
have in common, which are the things that are easiest to talk about.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re looking for ways to diversify your sources of social support, there
are many different kinds of non-work social groups related to your interests or
passions, such as a cultural affinity group, a political organization, a
volunteer organization, a sports or games group, or a spiritual community.</p>
<p>Developing non-overlapping sources of social support makes your social life
robust to shocks and helps you develop more depth as a person.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The spiritual dimension of food</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-04-the-spiritual-dimension-of-food/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-04-the-spiritual-dimension-of-food/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I baked a loaf of sourdough bread for the first time this week, which taught me&#xA;some lessons about how food affects my sense of identity. My lunch today was&#xA;very simple: two slices of sourdough bread with a bit of jam. To me, this plain&#xA;meal is at least twice as satisfying as a hamburger from any restaurant. I think&#xA;it has to do with something I&amp;rsquo;m calling the &amp;ldquo;spiritual dimension&amp;rdquo; of food. One&#xA;could also call it the &amp;ldquo;emotional&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;intangible&amp;rdquo; dimension of food, but I like&#xA;the idea of a meal having a dual nature that feeds both our bodies and our&#xA;spirits.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I baked a loaf of sourdough bread for the first time this week, which taught me
some lessons about how food affects my sense of identity. My lunch today was
very simple: two slices of sourdough bread with a bit of jam. To me, this plain
meal is at least twice as satisfying as a hamburger from any restaurant. I think
it has to do with something I&rsquo;m calling the &ldquo;spiritual dimension&rdquo; of food. One
could also call it the &ldquo;emotional&rdquo; or &ldquo;intangible&rdquo; dimension of food, but I like
the idea of a meal having a dual nature that feeds both our bodies and our
spirits.</p>
<p>The consumption of food provides us with the nutrients needed for life, but it&rsquo;s
much more than that, like a job is more than just a source of income. Decisions
about what we eat, how we eat, and with whom we eat are important components of
the development of identity.</p>
<p>The spiritual dimension of food is those components of food decisions that
contribute to the nourishment of our spirits &mdash; the intangible parts of who we
are. These are our connections to other people, connections to our environment,
and our knowledge, preferences, and abilities.</p>
<p>For me, the decision to make and eat sourdough was partially motivated by a
desire to be more involved in the food that I eat. By cooking for myself, I take
more responsibility for my nutrition. I am responsible for selecting and
preparing the ingredients. I reduce external dependencies on the (flavor and
price) preferences of other people. Simultaneously, I increase my ability to
provide for other people &mdash; now that I know how to make sourdough bread, I can
(and did) share it with other people. Being more involved in the details of my
life gives me power to modify my life in the ways that I choose.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I fixed some chairs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-03-i-fixed-some-chairs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-03-i-fixed-some-chairs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I fixed some chairs and it was the most satisfying thing I did all day.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My wife bought some used chairs yesterday, and she noticed after bringing them&#xA;home that they were a little wobbly. This evening, I pulled out my tools and&#xA;started tightening screws to see if I could fix the problem.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the process, I discovered that one of the chairs had been put together&#xA;incorrectly, with two of the legs having been swapped. Because it&#xA;was put together wrong, it was very wobbly and some of the pieces were jammed&#xA;together at crooked angles.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today I fixed some chairs and it was the most satisfying thing I did all day.</p>
<p>My wife bought some used chairs yesterday, and she noticed after bringing them
home that they were a little wobbly. This evening, I pulled out my tools and
started tightening screws to see if I could fix the problem.</p>
<p>In the process, I discovered that one of the chairs had been put together
incorrectly, with two of the legs having been swapped. Because it
was put together wrong, it was very wobbly and some of the pieces were jammed
together at crooked angles.</p>
<p>Being able to sit down with a set of tools, diagnose a problem, and make the
world a better place in just half an hour is a wonderful thing to experience. It
wasn&rsquo;t a big fix, but it greatly improves the experience of sitting in those
chairs.</p>
<p>I think everybody needs moments like this. Everyone needs to experience
regularly the satisfaction of problem-solving on a short timescale. Most of the
things I do on a daily basis do not give me immediate rewards, and that makes it
important that I find things that do give me immediate satisfaction&mdash;running,
cooking, and playing with my daughter are examples that come to mind.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reasons being a parent is awesome</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-02-reasons-being-a-parent-is-awesome/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-02-reasons-being-a-parent-is-awesome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I want to share some of the reasons being a parent has been (somewhat&#xA;unexpectedly) so good for me personally. I think these reasons will apply to&#xA;almost every parent.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Before I start, I want to make it clear my goal is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to convince everyone to&#xA;have kids, but rather to show that parenthood is awesome in a couple of ways&#xA;that I don&amp;rsquo;t think get talked about enough.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I want to share some of the reasons being a parent has been (somewhat
unexpectedly) so good for me personally. I think these reasons will apply to
almost every parent.</p>
<p>Before I start, I want to make it clear my goal is <em>not</em> to convince everyone to
have kids, but rather to show that parenthood is awesome in a couple of ways
that I don&rsquo;t think get talked about enough.</p>
<h2 id="being-your-child-s-parent-has-limited--or-no--competition">Being <em>your</em> child&rsquo;s parent has limited (or no) competition</h2>
<p>Competition to be your child&rsquo;s best parent is extremely limited. Unlike your
professional interests (and likely your hobbies), the odds are pretty good that
the pool of people trying to parent <em>your child specifically</em> is small. Sometimes,
it might be a pool of one. I certainly feel that I&rsquo;m only competing against
myself&mdash;that my wife and I occupy different, non-competitive niches in our
daughter&rsquo;s life. Within my niche, I am number one; undefeated! It doesn&rsquo;t matter
to me that there isn&rsquo;t really anyone I&rsquo;m competing against&mdash;it still gives me
satisfaction to know that I am the best at what I do.</p>
<p>Furthermore, whatever you do for your child is going to be a large fraction of
their life experience. It doesn&rsquo;t matter very much if the things you do for them
are imperfect&mdash;what matters more is that you try. Just trying can get you to
the top of the leaderboard&mdash;but you have to try.</p>
<h2 id="being-a-parent-is-orthogonal-to-other-interests">Being a parent is orthogonal to other interests</h2>
<p>How good of a parent you are can be completely uncorrelated with your
professional success, your financial situation, or your hobbies. This
decorrelation between parenting and the rest of your life makes it easier to
still feel like a success, even if the only thing you&rsquo;re succeeding in is being
a good parent to your child.</p>
<h2 id="being-a-parent-is-a-great-mix-of-instant-and-delayed-gratification">Being a parent is a great mix of instant and delayed gratification</h2>
<p>There are two kinds of work&mdash;work that has instantaneous rewards, and work that
has delayed rewards. In my experience, optimal productivity and happiness in
one&rsquo;s work requires a mix of both kinds of work.</p>
<p>Working without any short-term feedback on how you&rsquo;re doing makes it difficult
to improve. Also, a lack of short-term rewards in your work will make each day
exhausting, because at the end of each day you can be left thinking &ldquo;What did I
do all that work today for?&rdquo;</p>
<p>On the other hand, work that only has short-term rewards will never build up to
a lifetime of achievement that you can look back on with satisfaction. You might
be happy on each individual day, but the overall narrative arc is missing.</p>
<p>Parenting, in my opinion, has the perfect mix of short-term and long-term
rewards. In the short-term, it is generally rewarding to spend any amount of
time with your kids doing something they enjoy. In the long-term, the things you
work to teach them (both knowledge and values) can gradually shape your child
into a fully-fledged human that you are happy to associate with.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning by boundary seeking</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-01-learning-by-boundary-seeking/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-01-learning-by-boundary-seeking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last year since I became a parent, I&amp;rsquo;ve had the wonderful opportunity to&#xA;observe how my daughter acquires new skills and learns about the world around&#xA;her.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Boundary seeking&amp;rdquo; is how I think of her main strategy for learning efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When she first encounters a new object, she pushes it to its limits. One day&#xA;last month she found a tote bag and played with it for the better part of an&#xA;hour. She dragged it around the room, she whipped it around her body as fast as&#xA;she could, she put her toys into it, she stepped on it, and of course, she put&#xA;it on her head, which she thought was hilarious. (Don&amp;rsquo;t worry, the tote bag is made from a&#xA;breathable mesh and she was totally supervised the whole time.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the last year since I became a parent, I&rsquo;ve had the wonderful opportunity to
observe how my daughter acquires new skills and learns about the world around
her.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Boundary seeking&rdquo; is how I think of her main strategy for learning efficiently.</p>
<p>When she first encounters a new object, she pushes it to its limits. One day
last month she found a tote bag and played with it for the better part of an
hour. She dragged it around the room, she whipped it around her body as fast as
she could, she put her toys into it, she stepped on it, and of course, she put
it on her head, which she thought was hilarious. (Don&rsquo;t worry, the tote bag is made from a
breathable mesh and she was totally supervised the whole time.)</p>
<p>By sampling over a large distribution space, she was able to find the most
interesting things that she could do with the tote bag. She got lots of
information about the way that the tote bag behaves under a wide variety of
conditions. As she discovered new, interesting behaviors (like putting the bag
over her head) she spend more time exploring them.</p>
<p>This is a very efficient way to learn. Essentially, you sample as big a space as
you can, then focus on the areas of that space that are most interesting to you.
My theory is that these &ldquo;interesting&rdquo; areas of the space represent boundaries on
a manifold, where one behavior changes into another. (Think, for example, about
how the bag might be good for carrying things when you carry it loosely, but
when you swing it around your head it makes a <em>whooshing</em> noise and it&rsquo;s more
fun.) The most efficient way to explore a high-dimensional space is to move
along boundaries, then use simple predictive heuristics to fill in the gaps
between boundaries.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book review: Poor Charlie&#39;s Almanac</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-09-30-book-review-poor-charlies-almanac/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-09-30-book-review-poor-charlies-almanac/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Poor Charlie&amp;rsquo;s Almanac is a collection of talks and essays by Charles Munger,&#xA;who together with Warren Buffett established Berkshire Hathaway as one of the&#xA;greatest investment funds of all time. The talks cover topics from accounting&#xA;practices to the role of psychology in business to general life advice for&#xA;finding happiness.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why you should read this book:&lt;/strong&gt; It&amp;rsquo;s fun to read and has good life advice. This&#xA;book exposes you to the mental models of a highly successful person. For me, the&#xA;biggest takeaway was the framework of &amp;ldquo;mental models&amp;rdquo; itself! I knew about&#xA;mental models, of course, but I had never thought specifically about the idea&#xA;that a collection of mental models of how the world works might serve as a&#xA;general-purpose system for problem-solving and understanding the world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Poor Charlie&rsquo;s Almanac is a collection of talks and essays by Charles Munger,
who together with Warren Buffett established Berkshire Hathaway as one of the
greatest investment funds of all time. The talks cover topics from accounting
practices to the role of psychology in business to general life advice for
finding happiness.</p>
<p><strong>Why you should read this book:</strong> It&rsquo;s fun to read and has good life advice. This
book exposes you to the mental models of a highly successful person. For me, the
biggest takeaway was the framework of &ldquo;mental models&rdquo; itself! I knew about
mental models, of course, but I had never thought specifically about the idea
that a collection of mental models of how the world works might serve as a
general-purpose system for problem-solving and understanding the world.</p>
<p><strong>Why you should not read this book:</strong> If you&rsquo;re looking for specific, quantitative,
actionable investment advice, this is not the right book for you. I&rsquo;m sure that
Buffett and Munger have plenty of quantitative ways that they analyze their
investments, but this is not that kind of book. This is a book that gives a
window into the author&rsquo;s philosophy and worldview.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Against additive solutions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-09-29-against-additive-solutions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-09-29-against-additive-solutions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was recently in a meeting where, multiple times, the default response to a&#xA;problem was &amp;ldquo;we should form a committee to respond to the issue&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;someone&#xA;should be appointed to take care of this issue.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I think this is a natural way to view problems and solutions. It&amp;rsquo;s a&#xA;human-centric view. In this view, problems get solved by people. When some&#xA;problem isn&amp;rsquo;t getting solved because it&amp;rsquo;s not in anyone&amp;rsquo;s job description to&#xA;solve the problem, the logical response is to either delegate authority and&#xA;responsibility for solving the problem to a person or a committee.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I was recently in a meeting where, multiple times, the default response to a
problem was &ldquo;we should form a committee to respond to the issue&rdquo; or &ldquo;someone
should be appointed to take care of this issue.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I think this is a natural way to view problems and solutions. It&rsquo;s a
human-centric view. In this view, problems get solved by people. When some
problem isn&rsquo;t getting solved because it&rsquo;s not in anyone&rsquo;s job description to
solve the problem, the logical response is to either delegate authority and
responsibility for solving the problem to a person or a committee.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a natural way to view problem-solving in organizations, but it&rsquo;s totally
wrong.</p>
<p>The first reason it&rsquo;s wrong is because it&rsquo;s what I call an &ldquo;additive&rdquo; solution.
The proposed solutions (forming a committee or appointing someone to address the
problem) will either add to the headcount of your organization or they will add
to the demands on people already at your organization.</p>
<p>What&rsquo;s so bad about additive solutions? It has to do with being able to predict
the downstream effects of the implemented solution. There is a fundamental
difference between a solution that involves adding a new component to a system,
versus a solution that takes away or modifies components that were already
there. When you add a new component, it&rsquo;s very difficult to anticipate all the
interactions that it will have with other components. In contrast, when you
modify or remove existing components, it&rsquo;s much easier to anticipate the
consequences by examining the role the component already plays in the system.</p>
<p>Additive solutions are slow. Creating a new component for your system is almost
certainly going to take more time than tweaking (or removing) something that&rsquo;s
already there. When starting from scratch, the design space is huge. In
constrast, when you&rsquo;re starting from an existing part, its attributes are mostly
fixed and you can think about a few dimensions that might need modification. At
the most extreme, you can decide to remove the component, which can be done
incredibly quickly.</p>
<p>Additive solutions are difficult to unwind. One a committee has been formed or a
person given a new responsibility, it is very difficult to turn back the clock,
even after the problem has been solved.</p>
<p>What&rsquo;s the alternative to additive solutions? Solutions that either modify or
remove existing components of the system. In my opinion, this is the most
effective way to solve problems because the problems are usually the result of
interactions of existing system components. Instead of adding downstream
components to solve problems that were introduced previously, why not go
upstream and prevent the problem from occurring in the first place?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing and worth</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-09-28-testing-and-worth/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-09-28-testing-and-worth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In standardized education the primary purpose of an exam is to measure how much&#xA;a student is &amp;ldquo;worth.&amp;rdquo; This is wrong. The primary purpose of an exam should be to&#xA;determine what the student knows.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What is it that people do with exam grades? They use them to compare students&#xA;against each other, as a way to determine which students are &amp;ldquo;better&amp;rdquo; than other&#xA;students. A grade serves much the same function as a price in a marketplace&amp;mdash;it&#xA;abstracts away all of the details until you have a single number that you can&#xA;use to compare unlike things. Grades are one of the primary metrics for&#xA;determining whether a student will be admitted to a university, admitted to a&#xA;doctoral program, or offered an internship or job. The primary purpose of exam&#xA;grades is therefore to determine which students are &amp;ldquo;better&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;worse&amp;rdquo; than&#xA;others, because that is how people use grades.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In standardized education the primary purpose of an exam is to measure how much
a student is &ldquo;worth.&rdquo; This is wrong. The primary purpose of an exam should be to
determine what the student knows.</p>
<p>What is it that people do with exam grades? They use them to compare students
against each other, as a way to determine which students are &ldquo;better&rdquo; than other
students. A grade serves much the same function as a price in a marketplace&mdash;it
abstracts away all of the details until you have a single number that you can
use to compare unlike things. Grades are one of the primary metrics for
determining whether a student will be admitted to a university, admitted to a
doctoral program, or offered an internship or job. The primary purpose of exam
grades is therefore to determine which students are &ldquo;better&rdquo; or &ldquo;worse&rdquo; than
others, because that is how people use grades.</p>
<p>I think it&rsquo;s wrong to abstract away all information about a student&rsquo;s knowledge
until all that is left is a single, crude numeric measure. When a teacher (or a
student) sees a grade, it is an extremely imprecise error signal.</p>
<p>The purpose of teaching is learning, and learning is better served by a precise
error signal, one which gives the student and the teacher feedback about what
the student does know and what the student doesn&rsquo;t know. Exams and grading must
be structured so that they are a measure of knowledge and knowledge gaps. Until
then, exams will be a measure of &ldquo;worth,&rdquo; and students who do poorly on exams
will view themselves as being unworthy or less valuable when they instead should
view themselves as just not knowing something yet.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time to write</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-09-27-time-to-write/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-09-27-time-to-write/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If writing down your ideas always makes them more precise and more complete,&#xA;then no one who hasn&amp;rsquo;t written about a topic has fully formed ideas about it.&#xA;And someone who never writes has no fully formed ideas about anything&#xA;nontrivial.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash;Paul Graham&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I think that the next phase of my self-education is writing. Here&amp;rsquo;s why:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing generates an error signal:&lt;/strong&gt; Writing externalizes your thought process,&#xA;which makes it easier to reflect on which of your thoughts need to improve.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>If writing down your ideas always makes them more precise and more complete,
then no one who hasn&rsquo;t written about a topic has fully formed ideas about it.
And someone who never writes has no fully formed ideas about anything
nontrivial.</p>
<p>&mdash;Paul Graham</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think that the next phase of my self-education is writing. Here&rsquo;s why:</p>
<p><strong>Writing generates an error signal:</strong> Writing externalizes your thought process,
which makes it easier to reflect on which of your thoughts need to improve.</p>
<p><strong>Writing is a form of retrieval practice:</strong> Retrieval practice is the best
known technique for building and strengthening long-term memory.</p>
<p>These two factors make writing a highly efficient learning technique.</p>
<p>Because I&rsquo;ve previously had a hard time writing consistently, I&rsquo;m making a
commitment: for the next month (until October 27th, 2024), I will write one blog
post every day. They probably won&rsquo;t be very long (or very good), but I&rsquo;m going to
write them.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;MD/PhD student in the United States&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Currently working on a neuroscience PhD&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jrasband/&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9548-7311&#34;&gt;ORCID&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/JoshuaRasband&#34;&gt;X (Twitter)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<ul>
<li>MD/PhD student in the United States</li>
<li>Currently working on a neuroscience PhD</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/jrasband/">github</a></li>
<li><a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9548-7311">ORCID</a></li>
<li><a href="https://x.com/JoshuaRasband">X (Twitter)</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
