<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Learning on Joshua Rasband&#39;s website</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Learning on Joshua Rasband&#39;s website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <managingEditor>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</webMaster>
    <copyright>Joshua Rasband (CC BY 4.0)</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Why I make my own flashcards</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-12-why-i-make-my-own-flashcards/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-12-why-i-make-my-own-flashcards/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During medical school, I started using the Anki spaced repetition system to put&#xA;large amounts of knowledge into my long-term memory. At first, I used decks made&#xA;by other students. Eventually, I found that I preferred creating my own&#xA;flashcards over using decks of pre-made flashcards.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;focus&#34;&gt;Focus&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Making my own flashcards is a significant use of time and effort. At first&#xA;blush, that sounds like it&amp;rsquo;s a disadvantage, but it can also be framed as a&#xA;benefit. Because there is a non-zero cost to making my flashcards, it&#xA;incentivizes me to make the minimum number of flashcards necessary and no more.&#xA;I found that before I started making my own cards, I was tempted to download&#xA;more decks than I reasonably had time to study. The cost incurred by making my&#xA;own cards helps me foucs my energies on just the facts that I want to remember.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>During medical school, I started using the Anki spaced repetition system to put
large amounts of knowledge into my long-term memory. At first, I used decks made
by other students. Eventually, I found that I preferred creating my own
flashcards over using decks of pre-made flashcards.</p>
<h2 id="focus">Focus</h2>
<p>Making my own flashcards is a significant use of time and effort. At first
blush, that sounds like it&rsquo;s a disadvantage, but it can also be framed as a
benefit. Because there is a non-zero cost to making my flashcards, it
incentivizes me to make the minimum number of flashcards necessary and no more.
I found that before I started making my own cards, I was tempted to download
more decks than I reasonably had time to study. The cost incurred by making my
own cards helps me foucs my energies on just the facts that I want to remember.</p>
<h2 id="ownership">Ownership</h2>
<p>Because I make my own flashcards, I have a deeper sense of accountability for my
study. When I see a &ldquo;bad&rdquo; flashcard (e.g. one that is poorly worded or
ambiguous) I know that it&rsquo;s my fault and I need to fix it. When using a deck
made by someone else, it&rsquo;s easier to ignore the card and keep studying without
improving anything. The knowledge that my flashcards are fully my responsibility
helps me keep iterating and making better and better cards.</p>
<h2 id="schema-construction">Schema construction</h2>
<p>The process of making flashcards helps me construct a schema into which I can
place facts. When I make flashcards, I have to ask myself what the most
important things to know are. As I organize my notes, it encourages me to think
about the relationships between concepts&mdash;how they are similar, how they are
different. By making flashcards, I give myself time to think about the facts I&rsquo;m
studying and how they are related&mdash;something I wouldn&rsquo;t be forced to do if I
were to rely soley on decks made by other people.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning vs. task completion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-04-learning-vs-task-completion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-04-learning-vs-task-completion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Optimize studying for learning, not task completion.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rote completion of a task is best done by specialization and division of labor.&#xA;The classical example of division of labor is &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Division_of_labour#Adam_Smith&#34;&gt;the making of pins&lt;/a&gt; &amp;mdash; by dividing&#xA;the making of a pin into many simple tasks and assigning a worker to each task,&#xA;pins can be made more efficiently than if every worker were to go through all&#xA;the steps of making a pin.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Optimize studying for learning, not task completion.</p>
<p>Rote completion of a task is best done by specialization and division of labor.
The classical example of division of labor is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Division_of_labour#Adam_Smith">the making of pins</a> &mdash; by dividing
the making of a pin into many simple tasks and assigning a worker to each task,
pins can be made more efficiently than if every worker were to go through all
the steps of making a pin.</p>
<p>In the quest for greater efficiency in my studies, I have fallen into the trap
of specialization of labor. If I&rsquo;ve already watched two or three lectures, I&rsquo;m
in a lecture-watching and note-taking frame of mind. If I&rsquo;m studying with
flashcards, it&rsquo;s easy for me to continue studying with flashcards. When I&rsquo;m &ldquo;in
the zone,&rdquo; the least effortful study task is to continue doing what I&rsquo;m already
doing. This feels more efficient because I&rsquo;m rapidly checking more things off my
to-do list, but it&rsquo;s not the most effective way for me to <em>learn.</em></p>
<p>Learning is not the same as checking tasks off a to-do list. Watching four
lectures instead of one in a single sitting doesn&rsquo;t mean that I&rsquo;ve learned four
times as much. On the contrary, I might experience information overload by
trying to absorb too much information in one sitting.</p>
<p>Learning needs to happen incrementally because new information and memories
decay quickly. Self-testing and reflection shortly after the first exposure help
consolidate ideas for long-term storage. Although task-switching while learning
is less efficient in terms of time used studying in a given day, information
will be better retained.</p>
<p>Learning is the cultivation of an interconnected garden of information and ideas
that live in your brain. Plants don&rsquo;t grow, die, or bear fruit all at once.
Neither do ideas. Effective study requires doing the right study tasks at the
right time, not just as quickly as possible.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning by boundary seeking</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-01-learning-by-boundary-seeking/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-01-learning-by-boundary-seeking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last year since I became a parent, I&amp;rsquo;ve had the wonderful opportunity to&#xA;observe how my daughter acquires new skills and learns about the world around&#xA;her.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Boundary seeking&amp;rdquo; is how I think of her main strategy for learning efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When she first encounters a new object, she pushes it to its limits. One day&#xA;last month she found a tote bag and played with it for the better part of an&#xA;hour. She dragged it around the room, she whipped it around her body as fast as&#xA;she could, she put her toys into it, she stepped on it, and of course, she put&#xA;it on her head, which she thought was hilarious. (Don&amp;rsquo;t worry, the tote bag is made from a&#xA;breathable mesh and she was totally supervised the whole time.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the last year since I became a parent, I&rsquo;ve had the wonderful opportunity to
observe how my daughter acquires new skills and learns about the world around
her.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Boundary seeking&rdquo; is how I think of her main strategy for learning efficiently.</p>
<p>When she first encounters a new object, she pushes it to its limits. One day
last month she found a tote bag and played with it for the better part of an
hour. She dragged it around the room, she whipped it around her body as fast as
she could, she put her toys into it, she stepped on it, and of course, she put
it on her head, which she thought was hilarious. (Don&rsquo;t worry, the tote bag is made from a
breathable mesh and she was totally supervised the whole time.)</p>
<p>By sampling over a large distribution space, she was able to find the most
interesting things that she could do with the tote bag. She got lots of
information about the way that the tote bag behaves under a wide variety of
conditions. As she discovered new, interesting behaviors (like putting the bag
over her head) she spend more time exploring them.</p>
<p>This is a very efficient way to learn. Essentially, you sample as big a space as
you can, then focus on the areas of that space that are most interesting to you.
My theory is that these &ldquo;interesting&rdquo; areas of the space represent boundaries on
a manifold, where one behavior changes into another. (Think, for example, about
how the bag might be good for carrying things when you carry it loosely, but
when you swing it around your head it makes a <em>whooshing</em> noise and it&rsquo;s more
fun.) The most efficient way to explore a high-dimensional space is to move
along boundaries, then use simple predictive heuristics to fill in the gaps
between boundaries.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
