<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Food on Joshua Rasband&#39;s website</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/food/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Food on Joshua Rasband&#39;s website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <managingEditor>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</webMaster>
    <copyright>Joshua Rasband (CC BY 4.0)</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/food/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The spiritual dimension of food</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-04-the-spiritual-dimension-of-food/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-04-the-spiritual-dimension-of-food/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I baked a loaf of sourdough bread for the first time this week, which taught me&#xA;some lessons about how food affects my sense of identity. My lunch today was&#xA;very simple: two slices of sourdough bread with a bit of jam. To me, this plain&#xA;meal is at least twice as satisfying as a hamburger from any restaurant. I think&#xA;it has to do with something I&amp;rsquo;m calling the &amp;ldquo;spiritual dimension&amp;rdquo; of food. One&#xA;could also call it the &amp;ldquo;emotional&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;intangible&amp;rdquo; dimension of food, but I like&#xA;the idea of a meal having a dual nature that feeds both our bodies and our&#xA;spirits.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I baked a loaf of sourdough bread for the first time this week, which taught me
some lessons about how food affects my sense of identity. My lunch today was
very simple: two slices of sourdough bread with a bit of jam. To me, this plain
meal is at least twice as satisfying as a hamburger from any restaurant. I think
it has to do with something I&rsquo;m calling the &ldquo;spiritual dimension&rdquo; of food. One
could also call it the &ldquo;emotional&rdquo; or &ldquo;intangible&rdquo; dimension of food, but I like
the idea of a meal having a dual nature that feeds both our bodies and our
spirits.</p>
<p>The consumption of food provides us with the nutrients needed for life, but it&rsquo;s
much more than that, like a job is more than just a source of income. Decisions
about what we eat, how we eat, and with whom we eat are important components of
the development of identity.</p>
<p>The spiritual dimension of food is those components of food decisions that
contribute to the nourishment of our spirits &mdash; the intangible parts of who we
are. These are our connections to other people, connections to our environment,
and our knowledge, preferences, and abilities.</p>
<p>For me, the decision to make and eat sourdough was partially motivated by a
desire to be more involved in the food that I eat. By cooking for myself, I take
more responsibility for my nutrition. I am responsible for selecting and
preparing the ingredients. I reduce external dependencies on the (flavor and
price) preferences of other people. Simultaneously, I increase my ability to
provide for other people &mdash; now that I know how to make sourdough bread, I can
(and did) share it with other people. Being more involved in the details of my
life gives me power to modify my life in the ways that I choose.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
