<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Productivity on Joshua Rasband&#39;s website</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/productivity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Productivity on Joshua Rasband&#39;s website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <managingEditor>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</webMaster>
    <copyright>Joshua Rasband (CC BY 4.0)</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/productivity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Better is better than more</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-23-better-is-better-than-more/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-23-better-is-better-than-more/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most of the time, when I say &amp;ldquo;I should be doing more&amp;rdquo; what I &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be saying is&#xA;&amp;ldquo;I should be doing things differently.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s often assumed that we could always be doing &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt;. Exercising more, sleeping&#xA;more, working more, reading more… more, more, more. I&amp;rsquo;m not convinced that&amp;rsquo;s&#xA;true.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are 24 hours in a day, and we spend each minute of the day doing&#xA;&lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;. We&amp;rsquo;re never going to be able to fit more than 24 hours of time into a&#xA;day. The task left to us is to determine &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; we&amp;rsquo;re going to use the time we&#xA;have.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Most of the time, when I say &ldquo;I should be doing more&rdquo; what I <em>should</em> be saying is
&ldquo;I should be doing things differently.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s often assumed that we could always be doing <em>more</em>. Exercising more, sleeping
more, working more, reading more… more, more, more. I&rsquo;m not convinced that&rsquo;s
true.</p>
<p>There are 24 hours in a day, and we spend each minute of the day doing
<em>something</em>. We&rsquo;re never going to be able to fit more than 24 hours of time into a
day. The task left to us is to determine <em>how</em> we&rsquo;re going to use the time we
have.</p>
<p>Why is this distinction important? Psychologically, it can be daunting to think
about adding things to our to-do list without taking anything away. I&rsquo;ve found
it&rsquo;s helpful to think about how I should be doing things better rather than how
I should be doing more.</p>
<p>My success rate for behavioral modification improves when I&rsquo;m able to identify
how existing components of my daily life will be modified or replaced by
something better. Instead of planning to complete a task at a vague
&ldquo;sometime,&rdquo; I can identify a specific time of day at which I will change my
behavior from what was previously planned. This dramatically increases my
chances of success.</p>
<p>This principle also applies in large organizations and bureaucracies. Better is
superior to more.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deliberate practice of self-mastery</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-17-deliberate-practice-of-self-mastery/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-17-deliberate-practice-of-self-mastery/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The single most important factor for success is having self-mastery.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Self-mastery is difficult to teach, but it can be cultivated. The key is to&#xA;developing self-mastery is proper stewardship of the reward circuits of your&#xA;brain. You need to make sure that your brain sends reward signal in ways that&#xA;will direct you to achieve your goals.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The main way that I have accomplished this is through deliberate practice. Every&#xA;time I want some kind of reward or break, I push myself to work just a little&#xA;longer before I reward myself. Then, when I accomplish my goal, the sense of&#xA;reward is associated with self-mastery, rather than giving in, thereby&#xA;reinforcing a sense of pleasure at delayed gratification.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The single most important factor for success is having self-mastery.</p>
<p>Self-mastery is difficult to teach, but it can be cultivated. The key is to
developing self-mastery is proper stewardship of the reward circuits of your
brain. You need to make sure that your brain sends reward signal in ways that
will direct you to achieve your goals.</p>
<p>The main way that I have accomplished this is through deliberate practice. Every
time I want some kind of reward or break, I push myself to work just a little
longer before I reward myself. Then, when I accomplish my goal, the sense of
reward is associated with self-mastery, rather than giving in, thereby
reinforcing a sense of pleasure at delayed gratification.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m now at a point where a lot of the pleasure in my day comes from the
knowledge that I have successfully achieved my goals. On nights when I force
myself to do the dishes and finish my homework before I let myself have dessert,
it&rsquo;s the sense of accomplishment that is the bigger reward.</p>
<p>This is a difficult pattern of thought to cultivate. It&rsquo;s taken me almost a
decade to get here. The rewards are enormous, however. The ability to say no to
basically any distraction or temptation in favor of accomplishing my goals has
been of critical importance as I try to balance my many responsibilities and
goals.</p>
<p>As a final note, self-mastery does not have to mean that every waking moment is
spent working or studying. It just means that your decisions are more fully
yours. I have found that self-mastery has actually increased my enjoyment of
leisure activities, because I can engage in them with the knowledge that I have
picked leisure because it is what I want to do, not because it is easy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sabbaths and anti-sabbaths</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-06-sabbaths-and-anti-sabbaths/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>contact@jrasband.com (Joshua Rasband)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-10-06-sabbaths-and-anti-sabbaths/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How a day dedicated to the profane improves my well-being&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;https://alexanderell.is/posts/infinite-scroll/&#34;&gt;lizard brain&lt;/a&gt; was losing the battle against the internet.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I kept finding interesting things that I just &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to read. I knew from past&#xA;experience that it was unreasonable to attempt quitting reading things on the&#xA;internet altogether. I might &amp;ldquo;get clean&amp;rdquo; for a few days or a few weeks, but&#xA;invariably there would be &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; I felt was worthy reading material and I&amp;rsquo;d&#xA;be back to my old ways. I felt like the optimal amount of time spent reading&#xA;news and blog posts was non-zero, but it also wasn&amp;rsquo;t multiple hours per day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>How a day dedicated to the profane improves my well-being</em></p>
<p>My <a href="https://alexanderell.is/posts/infinite-scroll/">lizard brain</a> was losing the battle against the internet.</p>
<p>I kept finding interesting things that I just <em>had</em> to read. I knew from past
experience that it was unreasonable to attempt quitting reading things on the
internet altogether. I might &ldquo;get clean&rdquo; for a few days or a few weeks, but
invariably there would be <em>something</em> I felt was worthy reading material and I&rsquo;d
be back to my old ways. I felt like the optimal amount of time spent reading
news and blog posts was non-zero, but it also wasn&rsquo;t multiple hours per day.</p>
<p>Eventually I solved my problem by borrowing and inverting an ancient practice:
the Sabbath. In some faiths, the core idea of the Sabbath is that it&rsquo;s a holy
day of rest occurring one day per week, a day not to be profaned by certain
activities such as work, commerce, or recreational pursuits.</p>
<p>However, instead of refraining one day per week from the &ldquo;unholy&rdquo; activities of
reading news and blog posts, I flipped it around: one day per week would be set
aside for these &ldquo;unholy&rdquo; activities, and one day only. I call this day my
&ldquo;anti-Sabbath.&rdquo; I chose mine to be on Friday.</p>
<p>The anti-Sabbath has multiple advantages. First, it&rsquo;s a stronger argument, even
if it&rsquo;s less rational. Why can&rsquo;t I read Scott Alexander&rsquo;s <a href="https://astralcodexten.substack.com/p/every-bay-area-house-party">latest</a> <a href="https://astralcodexten.substack.com/p/another-bay-area-house-party">installment</a> <a href="https://astralcodexten.substack.com/p/even-more-bay-area-house-party">of</a>
&ldquo;Bay Area House Party&rdquo;? Because it&rsquo;s not Friday yet. My old argument against
reading blog posts was mostly an appeal to productivity, which is a much weaker
argument. I could always rationalize that I&rsquo;d really be more productive after a
little break, or that it will be a really fast break and then I&rsquo;ll get back to
work. In contrast, I can&rsquo;t argue very much about which day of the week it is.</p>
<p>Second, the anti-Sabbath helps me be more efficient with my reading. Instead of
spreading my internet browsing out over the course of a week, I have to pack it
into a single day, in addition to all of the other things I already have to do
that day. By the time I get around to reading all the new links in my RSS reader
or checking the top page of HackerNews, I&rsquo;m short on time and I can&rsquo;t afford to
read things that are only slighly interesting to me. I discard links I&rsquo;m not
very interested in, which ends up being about half of what shows up in my RSS
reader. If I start reading something and discover that it&rsquo;s not very good, I&rsquo;ll
stop reading it. Having limited time in which to enjoy the week&rsquo;s news and other
reading helps me use that time effectively.</p>
<p>Third, the anti-Sabbath turns what was once an escape into a chore. Compressing
all of my reading into one evening makes it a far less enjoyable experience than
if I were to spread it out over the course of a week. Making my distraction
reading an unpleasant experience makes it much, much easier to resist on every
other day of the week. This has been great for breaking my habit of compulsively
checking newsfeeds such as HackerNews.</p>
<p>Finally, anti-Sabbaths help alleviate the fear of missing out that I would get
from trying to quit altogether. When I&rsquo;m worried that I could be missing
important events, I can remind myself that really important things will still be
headlines by the end of the week, and the things that don&rsquo;t matter by the end of
the week aren&rsquo;t worth reading at all.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
